Let's talk here about what he
said that the first level of
morality, the perfection of
morality,
is called morality that
helps other
people, this is the third level of
morality, the second would be to
avoid good karma, the first level of morality is
to avoid harming other people, the
second level is to create good karma,
helps other people, the third level is to
take care of others, the
third level of morality is to take care
of the
world, he
says, if you want an example, he
says,
say these are four ways to treat
students, this
type of
morality is to treat students
well - this is the highest type of
morality, these are four ways, they are
called that, the name in the ancient
language is four ways to gather
students, the
first is not in the book, I took it from
another book, for you,
one of these books is Jen kap,
Ocean
of Argumentation, this is a commentary on the work of
Nagar. This was an old man who
spent
years translating Tsongkhapa's commentary on Dar
Marta, and if you have nothing else to
do, you can spend 12
years on this book. This is my secret plan,
it will be 3,000 pages. He says,
here is the MBA, which
means attracting students with your
generosity, giving them hundreds of dollars for
small
answers, for simple
answers, being very generous to
students always feed them Too much even
feed My teacher did it very well
so I came to him
say kotso tso mtso
tso this is students should come to
class no
good
drinks
snacks in any
case You must attract students with
your super
generosity I learned this Thanks to my
teacher We bought
cars at
home We had a friend there is a doctor
who helps students when they really
need it this is the first of the four ways of
higher
morality what they
love Study your students what they
like what they like to drink eat
what they like to do Study
them they should be How is your lamrim your
students this is your lamrim you must study
your students and figure out what they
like and attract them like honey for
[music]
bees
What does
sushi do with a bee
Who is a
bee
okay You should say some kind of
American Kyoto joke first you need to
learn to understand what
students want and give it to them and you can have
failures and I have had failures many
times we
talked in New York when I started
teaching I have had failures many times
I had a debt of 30,000 dollars,
now it's like 100,000 dollars when I
finished
Diamond because I paid for
everything. I remember
many years ago. It took a long time to
pay off this debt. I paid for everything.
Don't be cheap, don't worry about
it. It will take a little time, but you will manage in the
end.
You will never lose money. If
you support your students, you
will always be happy and by the gods, you will
always be comfortable
with your students. If you want to spend money,
spend it, but don't worry about it.
Just do it. Shut up and
do it. Take care of your students. Everything
they need. Let's take care of them.
It's very, very
fun. All of Buddhism is fun. I think
it should be called "We Have Fun" instead of "
Buddhism." It's eternal all
day long.
Second, praise your students too much.
Oh, you're so smart. I've
never had such smart students. How are
you doing this? Wow,
you helped one grandmother. You
must be so great. You are bahi satva. All
they do is raise children.
When you have
children, every mother  Praises her kids like
crazy Oh you're so You're the smartest
kid in the whole
town I'm such a lucky mom to have
you Don't ever lie
Just give it a little more Just a
little bit of an interception Just a little bit Be inspired
Rejoice The little things they
do You're right Oh you're so smart and they
They made 10 mistakes Don't pay
attention Just don't
notice They're
kids We were talking Talking to
Sophie
She was talking about her daughter Daughters
inspire them Of course they make 10
mistakes When they do one thing well
But ignore it
And they don't correct their mistakes But you
have to wait Sometimes you wait a very long time For a
student to do at least something
well And then you oh You're
simply the best
student Be inspiring - That's
real Buddhism Be generous with
your
[music]
students
If you make mistakes with your students
It means you're a good teacher I've done it
many times Even even
today I wanted to leave a 10 dollar
tip in the room But I don't have money I'm like Damn
Don't look at your students' mistakes
Kids Just
be inspired by at least something good
Say Oh you are the best
child this is the
director
third Don
Say Don this means do
n't tolerate when your
Students don't do what they
promised And
inspire them to actually do something
don't inspire them to be
lazy it's not enough that you have
Vete rims
they don't
do anything Teach your students
Buddhism but
then make sure they do something and
that's the
difference We are not trying to
raise learned Buddhists we are trying to
raise people
Buddhists so that they do something That's
great Let them take Buddhism into their
lives and not in their
mouths number four the hardest is 100
dollars and you teachers are silent That's an
easy woman
Question number four
example Yes 100
dollars Katinka is correct Which one here
Yes as a teacher You
must
do what you teach the highest morality of a teacher
What are you
saying This is like personal advice to be a
teacher and not follow what
you are learning is schizophrenia this is very
wrong It will drive you crazy
you will go crazy You go to
class  and you say everyone
should put down their gadgets at 10
pm
and if you yourself don't do it then you're
schizophrenic you're just going
crazy it's not great to teach
Buddhism If you don't do it
yourself you will be unhappy you will be more
unhappy I can tell you for sure
because in my life this happened
if you don't follow what you teach
you feel
dirty number what's higher the highest advice for
teachers do what you teach others
if you can't do it then
shut up and don't do it and don't talk
about
it then This is not just not just an
old teacher keep working on
yourself never give up keep
following what you learn
never give up Oh I can't
do this I teach
them to put down their gadgets but secretly I
sleep with my phone and look at bad things on my
phone at night It will drive you crazy
Try to
stop this Try to do what
you teach what you
learn and I do what I
teach by the way But what I'm telling
you if you do this  you won't do it if
you have secrets and you don't want your
students to know what you're not doing because
teaching is uncomfortable and
they can
feel it And you're like it's 10 o'clock
You should put your
phone down don't watch any nasty stuff after
10 pm and the students are
like something's unpleasant here they
can feel
it no one can be a perfect
liar you will have
some subconscious expressions
you won't move naturally When
you lie as a teacher everyone knows
Sorry everyone will know
This is on the one
hand a teacher who doesn't want to
change he will be more and more
experienced in hiding his
mistakes but
this
won't change him and then he will be
proud I can say I give my
computer to Rob at 10 pm I've been
giving my computer to him at 10 pm for a year now and you
can feel that your
teacher is telling the truth and when he's
telling a lie You can feel it too
and if you do
something wrong somewhere just clean it
[music]
Like your mom comes into your room and
sees your dirty room and you can
lie to her that you cleaned the room but it's
easier to clean the
room we are not
perfect we will make mistakes and I'm
not saying that you should give up
learning you should just
clean your room every day It's getting better and better no
one is a perfect teacher no
teacher is perfect except for
my teacher of course but I'm telling you
that we all make mistakes and be
honest If you stand up and say I'm a
teacher I'm a Buddhist teacher and I made these
mistakes I participated in an abortion
when I was young very
young I'm honest I say this I don't want to
hide it be simple
and then you become a better teacher a
teacher who makes mistakes is better than a
teacher who pretends that he doesn't
make
mistakes Okay, I'll
follow and here's an interesting
list 11
ways you can help
your students
11 tips on how you can help students
number
one help
people Try for the sake of your
students and when your students have
problems
Come Be there with them I
have a student who has cancer
now and my wife and I We
invite him more often more often than before And
what What does it mean to come show up
Be there with him  help
him Be with him to share so that
he can share his problem with you
138,000 students
pupils you can't answer every
email I have 50,000
now don't go
crazy Be with the
students as much as you can
if you can't try to find someone
who can
do it for you number two
pay special attention to people who
don't know how to do what they should
do For example if you have a cafe in a
small
town and the manager doesn't know how to
make
money and loses your money every day
then teach
him politely cheerfully
Take him to another restaurant to have dinner
with him there together and say look It looks like you do
n't know how to make money
he will say Well yeah And then Help him there
is a special karma that we create
when we help people learn what they
don't know number three
[music]
pay kindness for kindness as a
teacher pay kindness for kindness don't
just say thank you for your
donation see you in a
year think about it and Express your
gratitude and help them too number
If you see someone who is depressed
or  Fear is a
time-saver to help this
person, or if you have 138,000 students,
then organize help. Find someone who
will help
them. Anyone who has problems in life or who is
afraid, help them. Number five,
especially
people who have experienced a loss in life,
who have lost family members or
money or a home or
health. Especially pay
attention to these people who are
sad, something happened to them.
So,
Ashoka shock means someone who does not have sadness.
Ashoka. If someone suffers from this, he has
lost a family member.
Especially, especially as a teacher, pay
special
attention. There is a long list of what a
teacher should do. A teacher
should have
a lot of time.
He should even sleep and
rest at the same time.
This is his responsibility. A
real teacher must learn
this. Pay special attention to
poor
people, people who have lost their country.
We have friends from Ukraine whom we
brought from Ukraine. My wife and I are sponsors of
several people. It's difficult, it's a lot of
money, but we enjoy
it and it gives us
joy.
They
work very well in our community. These
people
are the special karma of a teacher.
Pay attention to people who have nowhere to
live. This is called
necha, for example.  Someone is building a
house or renovating a house or someone
lost their home in the war or something like that.
Pay special attention to
this, especially as a
teacher. Even animals in this world should
have their own hole where they can run.
Really, people are animals or
animals. They should have their own hole
which is their home. If you found an animal
or you found a student who doesn't have a
place in English,
say that there is no place they can
call their home. Then
help people find it.
And the same with animals. We just
took one last week. We took a cat. Here's a
scratch. She
kissed me. She's
wild. We only get to know
her. Homeless people, homeless
animals. Pay special
attention if people are
fighting,
they have a struggle in the family or between
companies. Then as a teacher, as a
Buddhist who studies the perfection of
morality, pay special attention
to connecting these people in
conflict. As
Buddhists, you should have a
sensitive
nose. I don't have a sensitive nose. My
wife says you haven't changed your shirt for
2 weeks already and I'm like this. I don't feel
anything. She says yes. Your nose doesn't
work. It's interesting because if
she bakes a pie, I can do it.  I
feel it right away, but if I need to
change my
pants, she's like that, I don't want to wash my pants. A
Buddhist
should have a good nose for problems.
If you're in a group, especially a Buddhist
group, and people don't get along with each other, a husband
and wife, for example, a
Buddhist should do something. He doesn't
just look at it, he tries to
do something,
he tries to help. These people don't like each other, and he tries to help. Will it work out for
you or not? It doesn't
matter if a couple doesn't connect, a husband and
wife quarrel. You should do the best
you can to help them, but you can't
change their
karma. Some people, they just have the
karma to humiliate each other for years.
Good teachers, but they can't
fix it. You can't fix
people. Other people's problems, but you have to
try. You understand. There's a
difference. Especially for
a teacher, it's your responsibility
to try, but their karma is their karma. You
can't fix their
karma. Only they can change their
karma. If someone else could change
your karma, then there were
dead in this world. Because Buddha is
always here, and he does good. But people
still die. Buddha isn't  Can
people stop this? The Armed Forces are still creating wars. Bud can't
stop the war. Only we can
stop it. Do the best you can.
Try to help. It's your
responsibility. Don't upset anyone. You tried, tried,
tried, and
people. The Armed Forces still don't get along in the Buddhist
group. Okay, okay. Smile.
Try again tomorrow. That's all you can
do. Bud can't
change them. You do the best you can. Well, don't
go crazy. Just do what you
can. Oh, guys. It looks like you have problems.
Can I help you with anything? No, okay.
If you see someone. Who is doing something
cool. Go and help. Oh, I like
this project.
Marin. I didn't know anything about her. I
have a friend who
introduced someone. Ask her to clean my
house and she
trimmed the roses that had grown very large.
They grew and trimmed these roses.
She
tries to help us and says,
Gela, Your house is all in disarray. You
need to make your home comfortable and then you
can g. What will you be happier
if your home is more comfortable? I have a
book for you and she gave me this book
called Marie.  Condo
she writes about how to make your
home comfortable I never did this
but my friend whom I
hired she came and She did everything
neatly and
now I couldn't find
anything she said there is a card she made a
card this is here she made a map of
my house and I use it
quite often where is this I have
she read this book there is a series
on Netflix by Maria Congo and I talked
to her this week we will have a
class with her
She looks very young she has a
lot of
hair
but I invite you to come we will we
did the program together She is very
cool We had a good time with her
in
class I want to thank Sophie Chau
who made this possible
[music]
If someone does something
right If someone helps a lot of
people then support him
it's easy to help
people when it's important for a person to help
people who were bombed in the house but if
you see a person who is doing something
good Give
me money I like What are you doing it's great
Can I help them with something and
help if you see something
opposite when people create
problems for themselves then say something do something
I am a strange person and my wife
tells me about it
I don't like to upset other
people that is, someone does something
wrong And I don't say anything and he
does even worse and I don't say anything and
he gets into big problems And I still do
n't say anything My wife says
this is not kindness you should say
something if someone does something
wrong every
person is a
teacher or a Buddhist every
person if you see someone Who
does something that harms him or
harms others You should
say or
do something You should participate in this don't be
afraid to participate in this not too much not too
much but if someone does something that
will harm him in the future
Well politely You can
say something this is number 10 number
number when the
time comes to create miracles to help other
people You should
do this for example fly in
Nile or take a car with one finger
or
pay your bills early in advance
any
miracles and here there is a comment he
says we can do all this except
number
11 he seems to say this list
in NM 11 parts but number 11 if you can you ca
n't  Don't
worry about doing it yet. You don't have to do it yet, but
just
remember. When that day comes when you
can fly in the sky or lift a
whole house with your little finger. If you can help
someone, it's your duty to do it.
If you are capable of a
miracle, then you must do it. It's your
responsibility to do it when the
time comes. The right time is not just for you.
All forms of helping others are included in the
third type.
It's interesting. In English, in America,
morality means not killing, not
stealing, not cheating. And in
Buddhism, doing good things for others
is the second level of
morality, and doing absolutely
good things for others is the highest
level of
morality. Teach them to meditate.
Teach them to think about emptiness. This is the highest level.
If you are not ready to take
vows, a moral verse at least.
Promise to do, preserve, keep, 10
ethical
principles. To
improve yourself, you begin to
do something good for others. In
Buddhism, this is called
morality. When you try to
change yourself and care about other
people, this is
morality. What time should I be
silent? 20
minutes
11:30
12:30 Moscow time.
We  We
finished the perfection of morality and
we move on to the
perfection of not
getting angry is
difficult I like to call it generally
called patience I don’t tolerate this
word It’s not like you sit That’s it
I don’t often get angry my friends know
it’s rare I actually get angry but I
get upset it’s not about anger it’s about getting
upset Can you keep lunch
and batsa yes And you often get angry Yes almost
all the
time so this is breaking vows Well no I get upset
in a taxi I get upset
in a restaurant I get upset when someone
comes to clean my room at 3:30 in
the morning I don’t get upset I’m just
a little
angry This is the next perfection what’s
number This is number
three I don’t like to call it patience
for
tenye You have to go to the toilet and there’s
someone in the toilet and
busy this is
patience and not getting upset is
different because something happens
wrong all the time something happens Can
you stay joyful and as a
Buddhist Can you be in a good
mood when something wrong
bad happens Can you
laugh at yourself Can you
have fun when something bad
happens I don't
know Your car broke down We have a good
car
dream it's a classic We went to a very
high mountain and our tire got flat and
we were having fun
everyone's like And it
seems to me we fixed it in less
than 2 minutes We solved the problem in
less than 2 minutes we just found
Edmund who
did it all very
beautifully in the World Cup the essence of Buddhist patience
two parts the essence of Buddhist patience two
parts number one
what we call patience in
English That is when someone
harms you And you don't get
upset When someone harms you
you don't get
upset someone does something And you're
like Well
okay and the second part of Buddhist
patience is that
Yana in an interesting
matter the second part of this perfection
is Can you be
patient with
the problems that samsara creates for you
for example a surgical operation
or you  I have some health problems
and the doctor
says we can do this. We'll cut
you open. Actually, we'll cut you open twice.
You can
do it all at once. He says no, you won't be able to
get up because you'll be in a lot of
pain. We'll cut you open first, and then
when it's all over. We'll cut
you open again. I have a choice. He says no. Well, okay, fine,
it's like a Buddhist attitude to the
pain of life.
[music]
If you're alive, you'll have pain. If you're
alive when you die, the pain will stop.
If the pain stops, that
means you're
dead. And until that
moment, you need to be patient with
two things. Number one is
problems.
We know there's one extra thing
called a "
butt." They
don't give you a free
visa anywhere. Okay, a visa with a butt is the first
thing. Be a patient Buddhist. Be
patient with people who
create problems for you. That's only 50% of
patience. Be cheerful and
happy. When they tell you you
need two surgeries, not one. I think I was
telling the truth. Rob, when we went to the
doctor.  Every person was glad
to meet us, we brought them joy, we did it
well, Rob and I
came, we worked with these boring
people, doctors, nurses, and now it's time to
see, let's cut me open a
second
time, we both know there's no choice, we
need to do this, this is medical
treatment, we have to do it, so we
had fun, we had fun, why not?
Why be serious about this,
we have no choice,
Paulie and we had it so funny, even
during the operation, it was
fun, everything was fun, listen, there's no
reason why you should be unhappy. When
something hurts, because it will come,
pain will come, you can't stop it,
pain will be everything in this room, I'm just
first, I'm the leader,
it's
pleasure. And just have fun, why
not, you can't get rid of it,
if you have a human body, this will happen to
you. If you live in this
world, if you're a business owner, if you have
children, if you have a mother,
parents, if you live in a house in the
country, in the dirt
on the
ground, you're going to have problems, so have
fun. It's not like you should
sit and cut yourself. I'm not saying
that,
Gela. I'm very  I'm glad that
I create problems for myself and I say that
life will bring you problems if you are a
true Buddhist then you know how
to laugh at problems
we have to cut you up Cool We
had a
squirrel She loved to
eat and chew on wires in my under my
hood in the
car it cost me 6000 dollars
inside under the hood there are
wires that are
greased with
Ore oil and she loved to get under the hood and
chew on these wires and it cost a lot of
money But what can you do about it to
kill the
squirrel Yes I caught I caught these squirrels and
transported them far
away to
the neighbors this I am sharing the teaching
So we have two types number one people
who create problems for you this is
patience obviously But life creates
problems for you and as a Buddhist you have to be good about
it in fact as a
Buddhist you can't
talk swear when a squirrel ate your
car or you won the lottery it's the same thing
someone Dat m dol
wires 6000 dollars it's all the same
as for  Buddhist it's the same and you're
like Well, okay, it happened again, okay, it
happened again, okay, the squirrel
ate the wires again,
okay, what else can you do? Why get
upset about
this? You can only give yourself a heart attack.
In any case, this is prose,
important logic that is almost
impossible, impossible
to accept,
okay, that's
great, this lamrim, I
don't know,
it's the most beautiful
thing. This is actually the most beautiful thing.
You should read this every day before bed, like
lenses, there are asses
in the world, there are an infinite number of asses in the world,
they will never end, you understand,
you care about one, three more,
cockroaches appear,
Oops, in your house, they talk to young people, an
old man says to
young people, there is a
limit to these asses. When you are born,
and there is a line of asses in life, when
you are born, the first one appears, then further, further, further,
and they will
only end when you die, they will not
end until you die. You can
Boro with them,
destroy them, move to another house,
or go to another country, but you can
try to solve problems one by
one to destroy all these problems,
but you will die.  Before you
finish, there is a queue of these problems, there are a
million of them, and you have solved one problem. But there are
still 9,900,000 of them waiting.
You cannot
physically free yourself from all these
problems before you die. You don't have time. If
you do nothing, if you don't
eat or
wash, if you don't meditate, you
will only solve problems one after
another. They will not end before you
die. You will still do this.
Therefore, it is more
logical
to take care of your upset
state.
First, do not harm people who
harm you. Harm yourself.
Your upset state and then
you will cope.
For
$1,000, there is $1,000. I need to borrow
from someone. I will pay you
tomorrow. So, everyone woke up.
$1,000
question. What is Shanti Deva's famous example
of how you try to
stop all the people who
harm you and there is a system. You raise your
hand, and they give you a microphone. I am not just
handing out money. I need you to
speak into the microphone.
I told her that she is wrong. She pays me
$1,000. This is a great quote.  nde But
unfortunately this is not the one I was looking for but I
admire you she said it is
better to have a thousand than not to have she
said If you can do something about the
problem do it if you can't just
shut up No no no it's very difficult you're not
saying that Okay we refuse we
cancel
the deal Try to cover the
whole world with leather just buy a pair of
shoes you can't stop every
annoying person in the world
listen I'm an old man I tried and
I quickly and I couldn't stop everyone
who irritated me they're still standing in line
just Stop and Stop
your anger and then that's it You're done everything for the
rest of your life you're in a good
mood you see you can't stop
every person
who irritates you this you can't
cover the whole world with leather just
buy a pair of shoes take care of
yourself 500 dollars because she gave
cited a quote from Shanti Deva 500 dollars
to her destroy your anger it's the same
How to destroy all your enemies
destroy Anger How to destroy all your
enemies actually If you don't fight
your anger
If you don't fight your habit of
getting upset If you're not in  good
mood always every day all
day
anesthesia is a good solution for
this it gets worse and worse and worse
it doesn't help to stop all the
stupid people in the world but when you
try they
multiply because this
karma
is called
tapas tapas there
are two tapasam tapas this is a
Spanish
snack I'm not talking about this one but another
Sanskrit
practice in India in some
Hindu groups sometimes you need to
raise your hand and walk with your hand raised for 20 years
and it almost
disappears you sit in a circle around your
fire and look look how long
can you sit there and then you
become some kind of special person
but in
Buddhism
sitting in problems for 10 minutes 20 minutes
all day marrying them this is
cool see if you can do
this what my wife
did Buddhists don't try to avoid
people
who cause them problems they
on the contrary try to connect with them
want to work for me and why
Because you are such an ass with
you it will just help me with my
anger so really have fun
doing Buddhism don't be
too  Serious
Gela said I shouldn't be
angry another
picture No don't be upset the greatest
of all
taps and
48.1 here are the
hearts I just completed a new
level of
DCI it will be in November Jean yes in
December the fourth number
advanced DCI How to double your
productivity How to
double your business life How to
double the efficiency of your life or
family or
business people ask me a lot How
can you do so many things how do you do
it
How do
you finish so many things I have
companies and I manage them all I'm very
happy I'm relaxing and they ask me how
you do it I don't waste time on
problems I'm serious and I deliberately
use bad language he says in
fact
I'm doing
asses I'll tell you
The secret about
efficiency how to create success
mi your day someone happened Ahaha Well
okay thank you Goodbye someone deceived
you oh guy I hope I never see you
goodbye I don't fight with people I don't Waste
my time on this My friends know this and
I'm not interested
I learned this  the secret of life I don't want to
be an ass myself
it's the worst thing when you become an
ass myself I don't waste my life
on problem
people I don't worry about it and I teach you
young
people advice from an old man
to make your life effective
you had
operations maybe you better tell
your wife where your
things are I said thank you how many books have you
written I don't know Can you make a list
in case if you die I'm like
Okay
books He says Oh my
God how did you do that And I say I don't
fight with people
when people treat me badly or
do something bad
[music]
complaining Sorry I'd better write another book
I'll fight with you tomorrow come
tomorrow
please and your life
becomes so much better someone wants to
compete with you create problems Oh
great you want to
tell me something I'll listen Come on and he
complains And at this time I'm writing the next
book This is what perfection the third
third perfection we haven't finished it
we will finish it tomorrow but from my
heart from my heart this life is very
dracaena very beautiful
and not
let the unfortunate people
ruin your
day do you want to fight with me Cool Cool Okay
see you later I'm
going two absolute methods of secret
diamond The Diamond Way everyone is asking can you
teach us the diamond way Can I do it now
Tell me I'll be right back I need to go to the toilet
now and no one will stop you Yes and
you just don't leave the toilet write a
book in the
toilet This is the first method the second
How
cool is it if you have a problem in your family on the
weekend Like here is the weekend on Chinese
New Year and everyone
wants too much and if there is a
fight in the kitchen Take a glass of water
when the problem is too strong just
drop it just drop a glass of water and there is
glass everywhere and you are like stand still
no one moves and then you collect
glass from the floor and everyone forgot about their own about
their fight and struggle this is the
secret of an old man two secret
methods toilet and
glass just
Change people's concentration what
people concentrate on just get
distracted there is no time to be angry at
people you will die I tell
you I never thought that Yas but I
got old and you litter too those
Your life is precious. Your time is the
most valuable thing. It's worth more than a
million dollars a minute. Don't give
it to stupid
people. Say I love you. Go
annoy someone else. I'm
busy. I have other things to do. Don't
fight with people. Don't waste time. It's
always a waste. Time isn't
empty. See you
tomorrow. Goodbye.